One 150 million years ago,
1.5亿年前
as dinosaurs approached their golden age,
就在恐龙达到它们繁盛时期时
one group evolved along new and revolutionary lines.
有一类生物却朝着一个全新的方向演化
Although they retained many of their reptilian characteristics,
尽管仍然保留着某些爬行动物的特征
they acquired extraordinary new ones...
但它们已经具备全新的
..feathers.
羽毛
Feathers helped with insulation
羽毛帮助保温、隔热
and display.
展示（鸟类都爱秀）
But they offered something far more valuable.
但羽毛能提供更有价值的东西
The power of flight.
飞翔的力量
And for birds,that changed everything.
对鸟来说，这改变了一切
Birds have the freedom of the skies,to travel further and faster than any other group of animals
鸟类在空中享有自由，比其它任何动物都跑得更快、更远
and to seize opportunities in all corners of the planet.
能在地球每一个角落获得机会
But this freedom brings many survival challenges,
但鸟类也必须在生命中的一些关键时刻
which birds must tackle at pivotal moments in their lives.
应付由这种自由带来的生存挑战
Flying demands enormous skill and effort,
飞翔需要极高的技巧和力量
and nowhere is that more evident than here, in the foothills of the Peruvian Andes.
秘鲁安第斯山麓，没哪里比在这里更明显了
This female hummingbird hovers with precision in her quest for nectar.
这只雌性蜂鸟能在吸食花蜜时，稳稳地悬停在空中
Her wing and tail design allow her to fly in any direction.
它翅膀和尾巴的构造，能让它朝任何方向飞
But the male has a real problem flying.
但雄性在飞翔时却有问题
And this is why
这是由于
he's weighed down with two super-long tail feathers,tipped with cumbersome discs.
它被两根超长的尾羽所压，就像绑着两个沉重的盘
This is the marvellous spatuletail hummingbird.
这就是不可思议的凤尾蜂鸟
and these are his flags with which to seduce a mate.
这两根长羽毛也是它吸引异性的招牌
Waving them back and forth takes a lot of effort,
来回地舞动它们要花费很多的气力
even from the comfort of his perch,
即使是在舒适的栖息场所
but to win her heart he's got to go up a gear.
但为了赢得她的芳心，它必须一直努力
He must show her how well he can fly but it's exhausting work.
必须证明自己是多么善于飞翔，即便这是件苦差
It's so demanding he can only stay airborne for a matter of seconds
由于非常辛苦，它只能腾空几秒钟
before he needs a rest.
然后休息一下
He's struggling to impress her,so one last try.
它努力想打动她，作出最后一次尝试
The extreme effort and energy needed to hover means hummingbirds can only fly in short, sharp bursts.
由于极度的耗费体力，蜂鸟只进行短暂的爆发式的飞行
But most birds need to stay airborne for considerably longer,
但大部分的鸟需要在空中停留很长时间
and must find far more energy-efficient ways to get around.
必须找到更为节省体力的方式
Here in the Simien mountains of Ethiopia,
在埃塞俄比亚的Simien山脉
at a breathtaking altitude of 15000 feet,
海拔15000英尺的地方
lives a supreme aerial maestro.
生活着一种空中大师
The lammergeier.
髭兀鹰
This youngster glides on air currents rising from the mountain slopes below.
这头幼鹰乘着从山谷升上来的气流滑翔
His nine-foot wingspan can carry him hundreds of miles a day
它长达9英尺的翼展，能带它每天飞行几百英里
in search of animal carcasses,with precious little effort.
寻找动物的尸体，却花费极少的力气
He watches out for other airborne scavengers,like these griffon vultures.
它警惕着其它的空中拾荒者，如这只狮鹫
They lead him to some commotion on the cliffs, and maybe the chance to feed.
它们与它在悬崖上造成了一些混乱，或许是个进食的机会
But this youngster is not the only lammergeier to spot the opportunity.
但这头幼鹰并非唯一发现这个机会的
So too has this adult.
这头成年鹰也有份
The vultures quickly strip the carcass clean.
秃鹫们很快将尸体吃光了
It seems he's too late. But in fact he's timed his arrival perfectly.
看起来它太晚了，实际上抵达时间刚好
There's no meat left
一丁点儿肉都不剩
and that's exactly the moment that the lammergeier has been waiting for.
这正是髭兀鹰所期待的时刻
It's bones he's after.
它图的是那些骨头
The young lammergeier too homes in on the carcass.
年幼的髭兀鹰也来到这具尸体
Bones contain rich marrow fat,
骨头富含骨髓和油脂
but extracting it is not easy,
但要得到它们并不容易
especially when the bone is a solid four kilos and too big to swallow.
尤其是骨头重达4公斤，很坚硬，无法吞下
But lammergeiers have an extraordinary solution, thanks to their flying skills.
但是髭兀鹰有一种奇特的方法，这多亏它们的飞行技能
Soaring up on thermal air currents and positioning the bone parallel
将骨头抓起，乘着热气流飞起来
to his body to minimize drag,he soon reaches the perfect height.
它很快就爬到了一个完美的高度
From here he glides to a place he knows
从这里滑翔至一个合适的地方
where he can deal with the bone,
让它可以处理骨头
where there are giant rock slabs sit on the lip of an escarpment.
那里悬崖边上，有一块巨大的石板
The bone is smashed.
骨头撞碎了
The juices in his stomach are more corrosive than battery acid.
它的胃液酸性比蓄电池里的液体还要高
They dissolve the bone so that he can now digest the marrow.
能够溶解骨头，以便消化吸收骨髓
Others come looking for leftovers.
其它的则过来寻找剩下的
But their timing isn't ideal
但它们时机不好
because now the young lammergeier has his turn!
因为现在轮到幼年髭兀鹰了
They'd better mind their heads!
它们最好服从领导
Proficient bone smashing takes endless practice
熟练地丢骨头需要不断地练习
to find just the right height,speed and moment of release.
找到最佳的高度、速度和松手时机
Lammergeiers have long, broad wings,
髭兀鹰有宽大的翅膀
ideal for gliding great distances with maximum efficiency.
能以最大的效率滑翔很远
But on the island of Little Tobago in the Caribbean
但在加勒比海的小多巴哥岛上
lives a bird for whom aerial agility is of paramount importance.
生活着一种对飞行敏捷程度要求更高的鸟
The red-billed tropicbird.
红嘴热带鸟
Short, pointed wings give it great manoeuvrability and speed.
短小而尖的翅膀给了它们灵活性和速度
During the breeding season, these flying skills are tested to the limit.
在繁育期，它们的飞行技巧遇到了终极挑战
While one parent looks after the chick, the other must journey
当一方照看幼鸟时，另一方必须外出
far offshore, to gather small fish and squid from the surface waters.
远离崖壁，在水面捕捉小鱼和小乌贼
But the hardest part is getting food back to the island, because they share this airspace with thieves.
但最困难的是将食物送回来，因为它们与强盗为临
Magnificent frigatebirds,
强壮的军舰鸟
known as Man O' War birds,patrol high above.
人称鸟中战士，在高空巡视
These pirates are not trying to kill the tropicbird,
这些海盗并不杀死热带鸟
but force it to give up its catch.
但会逼迫它们放弃到嘴的食物
It's an aerial dogfight.
这是一场激烈的空战
Tropicbirds are quicker on the turn.
热带鸟在转弯时更快
Frigates have exceptionally lightweight bodies
军舰鸟的身体比例非常完美
and their extremely long wings give them great power.
超长的翼展给了它们巨大的力量
Success.
成功了
A favourite attack is from behind,and at height.
它们最喜欢在后面从高处袭击
There goes the fish -
鱼在那儿
another victory.
另一个胜利
This tropicbird chick still awaits the return of its parent
这只小热带鸟仍然在等待
who has yet to run the gauntlet of the pirates.
正在遭受海盗打劫的亲人的归来
Keeping close to the waves is his best chance.
尽量接近海面是它最好的选择
Frigatebirds have so little oil in their feathers
军舰鸟的羽毛里含油很少
they can't risk ditching.
它们不敢落在水面
If he can just reach the cliffs he'll be safe.
如果它刚好能赶到崖壁，就安全了
He's made it,with his crop still full of fish.
它做到了，带回满嘴的鱼
Red-billed tropicbirds rely on extreme aerial agility
红嘴热带鸟依靠敏捷度极高的飞行
to overcomethe many challenges of their life.
克服了生活中的许多挑战
For others,survival demands endurance.
对另一些鸟来说，生存需要忍耐力
Every spring, red knots
每个春天，红腹滨鹬
fly 10,000 miles from their wintering grounds in Argentina to their nesting sites in Canada.
会从阿根廷的越冬场所飞行10000英里到加拿大的筑巢地点
The only way they complete this marathon journey
完成这种马拉松式旅程的唯一方法
is by making a crucial fuel stop here in Delaware Bay,on the east coast of America.
是要在位于美国东海岸的特拉华海湾,作一次重要的停留休整
What is most extraordinary is that as well as having to find their way
最为奇妙的是，在找到这个地点的同时
to this one location, they must also time their arrival to perfection.
它们必须在抵达时机上也要恰到好处
They have a rendezvous with prehistoric creatures emerging from the deep
它们同海水深处的一种史前生物有个约会
which have hardly changed in 250 million years.
近2.5亿年来一直没变
They come ashore in greatest numbers on the highest spring tides.
它们在每年春潮最高时蜂拥而至
Horseshoe crabs.
鲎
The crabs are here to lay their eggs.
鲎在这里产卵
That's what the knots are after.
这也是红腹滨鹬们所追寻的
Most eggs are buried out of reach,
大多数的卵被埋起来吃不到
but some are accidentally dug up by other crabs.
但有些卵意外地被其它的鲎挖出来了
Most of the west Atlantic red knot population join this feeding frenzy.
绝大部分的西大西洋红腹滨鹬加入了这场疯狂地宴会
In a matter of weeks the knots need to rebuild their fat reserves
这是红腹滨鹬重新储存脂肪的关键几周
and double in weight.
体重倍增
To achieve this, each knot must eat as many as 400,000 eggs -
为了达成指标，每只红腹滨鹬要吃掉40万只卵
a tall order given the skill and effort needed to swallow just one.
这对每次只能吞下一只的它们来说，是个离谱的数字
Head down, feeding non-stop means it's hard to be alert to predators.
埋头不停地进食，意味着很难防范天敌
A peregrine falcon.
游隼
With egg laying complete,the horseshoe crabs now leave
产完卵后，鲎离开了海岸
these shores while the knots gather every last egg they can find.
红腹滨鹬会吃掉所有它们能找到的卵
It's time for the birds to move on.
鸟儿们该上路了
The knots still have a further 2,000-mile non-stop flight
接下来它们会有个2000英里的无间歇飞行
to reach their breeding grounds in Canada.
最终到达加拿大的繁育场所
Flight gives birds many advantages, but there's a period in their lives
飞翔给了鸟类很多优势，但这也有句点
when they are forced back down to Earth.
当它们必须回到地面时
The nesting season.
繁育期
This is the time when they are at most risk,
这是它们最为冒险的时期
so they must find the safest possible location.
所以它们必须寻找尽可能安全的地方
Few go to greater extremes than lesser flamingos.
极少有像火烈鸟这样极端的
They nest in the remotest corners of Africa's caustic soda lakes.
它们在非洲偏僻的盐碱湖筑巢
Like their reptilian ancestors,birds lay waterproof eggs.
就像它们的爬行类祖先，所产的卵是不透水的
Despite this,flamingos still protect theirs
尽管如此，火烈鸟依旧
on special mud-stack nests as the lake is prone to flooding.
将巢穴筑在湖水淹不到的特殊的泥堆上
It's also just a little cooler up here.
这里也会凉爽一些
Temperatures at ground level can reach a blistering 50 degrees Centigrade.
地表温度可能会高到50摄氏度
Once a chick hatches, it spends the first six days in the nest.
幼鸟孵出后，会在巢里呆上六天
This is when it's at its most vulnerable -
这也是它们最脆弱的时候
totally reliant on its parents.
完全依赖父母
The caustic mud deters predators.
强腐蚀性的烂泥能防御天敌
But the adult flamingos can cope in this quagmire, because of their long, scaly legs.
但成年的火烈鸟能行走自如，因为有细长的脚
Any chick that slips from the nest, however,
不小心从窝里滑出来的幼鸟
is treading on very dangerous ground.
行走在危险的地面
This parent encourages her chick to climb back to safety.
它的家长鼓励它爬回去
Raising chicks requires huge parental investment in both time and labour,
抚养后代需要父母付出时间和精力
wherever you are.
无论你在哪里
Few places are tougher than the Antarctic.
没地方比南极更为艰难
Chinstrap penguins.
颊带企鹅
Every day they travel up to 50 miles out at sea, hunting for krill.
它们每天去50英里外的海面捕食
But the hard part is getting this food back to the colony,
但困难的事情在于将食物带回栖息地
because it sits on the ice-free rim at the top of this giant volcano,Deception Island.
因为它位于一座环形大火山的顶部
For the returning fishing party, the first challenge is getting ashore.
从捕鱼宴会返回，第一个挑战就是上岸
The beach is steep,with a powerful undertow.
海滩很陡峭，还有力道十足的回头浪
This female lands safely, but she now begins a long journey on foot.
这只雌企鹅安全登陆，开始一段漫长的徒步行走
For a flightless bird,getting to the top of the volcano
对于不会飞的鸟，到达这座火山的顶部
means a gruelling climb,especially when glaciers,
意味着一次艰难的爬行，特别是
covered with muddy volcanic ash,stand in your way.
面前的道路是泥泞的火山灰和冰雪混在一起
It's like a game of snakes and ladders.
这就像一个蛇爬梯子的游戏
A combination of beak,wing tip and feet.
依靠嘴巴、翅尖和脚趾的通力合作
And she wins through!
它成功了！
Now she joins penguin rush hour.
它遇到了企鹅的下班高峰期
Almost home.
几乎到家了
She's reached the crater rim, but her trials are still not over.
它到达火山口的边缘，但对它的考验还没有结束
She must now try and find her family among more than a 150,000 birds.
现在它必须在近15000只鸟中找到自己的家人
Her hearing is so acuteshe can identify the individual cry of her own chick in the din.
它的听觉如此敏锐，能在喧闹中识别出自己孩子独特的叫声
She's made it and the family welcomes her return.
它做到了，家人热烈地欢迎它的归来
The result of all this parental effort - a mouthful of krill.
这一路的努力，回报是满嘴的磷虾
Now it's her partner's turn.
现在轮到它老公了
A chick's demands are endless.
幼鸟的需求是无止境的
Sometimes they can push parents to desperate lengths.
有时候会把父母推向拼命的境地
But birds are masters of improvisation.
但鸟类是随机应变的大师
Dassen Island, off the coast of South Africa, is home to a nesting colony of great white pelicans.
南非Dassen岛，是大型白鹈鹕的栖息场所
There are chicks of all ages all with a hefty appetite.
这里无论大小，所有的幼鸟都胃口十足
The parents have a formidable task.
它们的父母任务非常艰巨
These pelicans are among the heaviest flying birds in the world,weighing up to 10 kilos.
这些大鹈鹕是世界上最大的飞行鸟类之一，体重达10公斤
A V-formation is the most energy efficient means of flying.
V字型编队是最省力的飞行方式
It significantly reduces drag for the bird behind.
能够为后面的鸟减少阻力
Pelicans normally fish along the coast,
鹈鹕通常沿着海岸捕鱼
but a shortage of food supplies has forced them to look elsewhere.
但食物的短缺迫使它们去别的地方寻找
Cape gannets
角塘鹅
plunge deep, hunting fish beyond the reach of the pelicans.
扎入海水深处，在鹈鹕到不了的地方捕鱼
But the pelicans aren't after fish.
但鹈鹕不是冲鱼来的
Their sights are set on a bigger catch.
它们瞄着更大的家伙
Malgas Island is the nesting ground for some 60,000 Cape gannets.
Malgas岛是6万只角塘鹅的栖息地
Normally one gannet parent goes off fishing while the other looks after the chick.
通常，一只塘鹅外出觅食，另一只留下来照看幼鸟
But declining fish stocks means both parents are often away hunting at the same time,
但鱼类资源的短缺意味着，有时候父母双方同时外出捕食
leaving their chicks unguarded,
留下幼鸟没人照看
something which hasn't gone unnoticed by the pelicans.
这一点没有逃过鹈鹕的注意
Only chicks with parents at their side,
那些有父母照看的
or those too large to swallow,have a chance.
或者太大而吞不下的，才得以幸免
Back at the pelican colony,
回到鹈鹕栖息地
the parents regurgitate partially-digested gannet chicks
父母把消化得差不多的小塘鹅反刍一部分出来
for their brood.
喂养后代
Although most seabird colonies on the African Cape are in decline,
几乎所有栖息在非洲海岸的鸟类数量都在减少
the population of white pelicans nesting on Dassen is growing.
栖息在Dassen岛的大鹈鹕却在增加
When birds come together to breed,
当鸟儿们聚集在一起繁育
and before they commit to one another,
在它们把自己托付给另一方之前
they will often perform the most remarkable displays.
通常会有引人注目的展示表演
One of the most enchanting happens here, on the lakes of Oregon.
俄勒冈州的湖面上，最迷人的情景发生了
Clarke's grebes mate for life,but the female must test herpartner's continuing commitment,
克拉克e在寻找终生配偶，但雌性必须测试对方的承诺是否持久
and she does this by inviting him to join her in a ritualised dance.
她邀请他一起跳一支仪式化的舞蹈
To strengthen their bond,he offers her a gift.
为了增进感情，他送给她一份礼物
Now, with eyes only for one another,
现在，眼里只有对方
the faithful pair reach the climax of their dance.
这对忠诚伴侣的舞蹈进入了高潮
Other birds don't form pairs.
有些鸟类并不结伴
Instead a male tries to mate with as many females as he can.
相反，雄性试图尽可能地与多只雌性交配
Male sage grouse gather in the grasslands of Wyoming
雄性松鸡聚集在怀俄明州的草地上
to advertise their virility
通过华美的羽毛和骄傲的姿态
with a finery of feathers and proud posturing.
宣告自己的男子气概
Females are much drabber-looking,
雌性看起来土里土气的
but extremely choosy.
但是极端挑剔
They will only mate with the most impressive male,
只会同最帅气的雄性交配
and they judge a male's worthiness by the sounds he makes.
通过对方的嗓音来判断雄性的价值
Birds go to great lengths to impress their partners.
鸟类在取悦异性方面真是不遗余力
In the forests of New Guinea,
新几内亚丛林
they famously use colourful feathers and song to maximum effect.
它们以彩色的羽毛和优美的歌声来增强效果
Birds of Paradise.
鸟的天堂
But in the western part of the island, these flamboyant birds
但在这个岛屿的西部，这些爱炫耀的鸟
share the forests with a rather unassuming-looking character...
和另一种非常低调谦逊的鸟共处
the Vogelkop bowerbird.
Vogelkop造园鸟
He might lack the plumage,but he's got an extraordinary repertoire of song.
也许羽毛并不出彩，但是它有非同寻常的歌唱本领
And, he's a wonderful mimic.
它也是出色的模仿家
Those are pigeon wing beats.
鸽子振翅的声音
That's a modest tiger-parrot.
这是模仿虎皮鹦鹉
And that,a sulphur-crested cockatoo.
这个则是黄纹美冠鹦鹉
Even more surprising he's an avid collector,
更令人惊讶的是，它是个热心的收藏家
with a very appreciative eye for colour.
对色彩很有品位
This male favours red and orange flowers.
这只雄鸟钟爱红色和橙色的花
And he's very fond of fungus.
非常喜欢菌类
Not everything he collects stays where it should.
它搜集的每一样东西并非都呆着不动
He puts these treasures on display within and around a construction that has taken him years to build.
它把这些宝贝陈列在花费几年时间造好的建筑物里面，或着放在周围
A giant bower woven around a central sapling, carpeted with moss.
由一棵小树作支柱的大型房间，由苔藓铺成地毯
This grand design is no nest...
这个宏大的设计不是作为巢穴
it's the ultimate seduction parlour.
而是一个极具诱惑力的接待室
But he's not alone on this hillside.
但这个山坡上不止它一个
He's got six rivals within earshot.
在听得见的地方就有6个竞争对手
This one prefers darker colours, decorating his bower with deer dung.
这一只喜欢暗色调，用鹿粪球装饰自己的凉棚
And charcoal.
还有木炭
Visual effect is of crucial importance.
视觉效果是至关重要的
Clearly he hadn't planned on all this sprouting fungus.
显然，它并没预料到这些萌发出来的菌类
He and his nearest rival live a stone's throw apart.
它和它的竞争对手们相距一箭之隔
Competition is intense.
竞争很激烈
It's the dung-ball bower that is the first to catch the female's attention.
粪球凉棚最先引起雌性的注意
He withdraws,while she inspects his workmanship.
它退在一旁，她来视察它的作品
She's back again,and seems impressed.
她又回来了，看起来被吸引了
But on closer inspection she is less convinced.
但凑近一看，她又少了几分信任
Perhaps it was that sprouting fungus!
也许就因为那些讨厌的菌类！
Back at the flower bower,the male performs a dress rehearsal.
回到鲜花凉棚，雄鸟正在练习装扮
He senses she's watching.
它发觉雌鸟正在观看
This is the moment he's been working towards.
这正是它努力期待的时刻
His bower channels his song in her direction.
它的凉棚将歌声朝她的方向传递
A final check.
最终的检查
All is to her liking.
全是她所喜欢的
Few birds devote such craft,effort and ingenuity to achieve this life-defining moment.
极少鸟类会为这个决定终生的时刻 付出如此多的技巧、精力和智慧
But here on Kenya's Lake Bogoria,these massive pink slicks
但在肯尼亚的Bogoria湖，大片的粉红色
signal the start of perhaps the grandest courtship event in nature.
预示着也许是自然界最大规模的求爱事件开始了
In certain years, when the lake is at its richest,
在某些年份，当湖泊最为富饶的时候
more than a million lesser flamingos congregate to feed.
超过1百万只火烈鸟来此聚集
It's now, when they're in their prime, that they must find their preferred partner.
现在，首要的工作便是找到最佳情人
To do that they perform a remarkable promenade.
为此，它们进行了一场引人注目的表演
With heads held high and neck feathers ruffled,
头高举，颈部的羽毛皱起
making them look as pink as possible,
使它们看起来尽量的呈粉红色
more and more birds join in the courtship march
越来越多的鸟加入了这场求爱竞赛
and pairs begin to bond.
夫妻结对也开始了
Small groups merge with larger ones
小群体合并成大群
until almost 1,000 flamingos are on the move.
上千只火烈鸟都行动着
From the equator to the poles,
从赤道到两极
birds have found the most ingenious ways
鸟类找到了最为巧妙的方法
of overcoming the many challenges of life,
来战胜生命中的诸多挑战
and everything revolves around their unique attribute, feathers.
每一样都跟它们身上特有的羽毛相关
For the past three years, the Life team has filmed birds in every part of the world imaginable.
过去的三年来，Life制作组在能想到的地球每一个角落拍摄鸟类
Nowhere was the filming trickier than in the jungles of West Papua.
没地方比在巴布亚岛西部丛林拍摄更为棘手了
Here is found for me one of the greatest wonders
这里有对我来说，是鸟类中最有意思的景观
of the bird world, the display arena of the Vogelkop bowerbird.
Vogelkop造园鸟的陈列展示竞赛
13 years ago I was lucky enough to witness these spectacular builders,
13年前，我就曾有幸目睹它们的特殊作品
but filming the timid female and courtship behaviour was a different matter.
但拍摄这种胆小的雌鸟以及它们的求爱行为则是另一回事情了
And this was what the Life team set out to film.
这也是Life制作组动身前往的目的
Barrie Britton was the principle cameraman for this programme.
Barrie Britton是这个项目的首席摄影师
With over 20 years in the business,
从事此道20多年
not only is he an accomplished photographer
他不仅是一位有才的摄影师
but he has developed a deep understanding of and empathy for his subjects.
他这在这方面还有着深层次的理解，投入了很多感情
Although each one posed it's own unique challenges,
尽管每一项都会显现出它特殊的挑战
Barrie he did seem to spend an inordinate amount of time cooped up in his trusty old hide.
Barrie真的花了很多时间把自己藏在帐篷里进行拍摄
Think I may have misjudged the hide position, cos the sea's coming in the bottom of the hide.
想想也许我找错了隐藏地点，导致海水从帐篷下面漫上来
Well, that was 11 hours in my little box.
看，我在小帐篷里呆了11个小时
Barrie saved his most ambitious trip of the series until last.
Barrie一路上都保持着勃勃的兴致直到最后
It took a team of 40 people 3 days of tough uphill trekking to get to the filming camp.
摄制组一行40人花了三天时间跋涉，才抵达拍摄地点
I could complain about leeches,biting insects, the tough going
我本可以抱怨蚂蝗、咬人的虫子和艰难的进度
but, I really don't want to,this is great.
但是，我不会，因为，这次不同寻常
Seem to have lost everyone else,I hope I'm going the right way.
看起来我走丢了，但我希望我的路是对的
Oh, made it.
噢，到了
Completely shattered.
实在是累
The hard work had only just begun.
艰巨的工作才刚开始
Tomorrow with the help of their guides, the crew would go looking for the best bowers to film
明天，组员们会在向导的带领下，寻找最好的窝拍摄
but not before a cautionary tale from the local chief.
但当地酋长告诉他们一个故事
HE SPEAKS IN HIS OWN LANGUAGE
（他在讲本地话）
So when he first was shown the bower by his father
当他父亲第一次带他看那种“凉棚”
he, there were flowers there,
那里有很多花儿
and, as a 12-year-old child he wanted to grab them
他，一个12岁的小孩，想去摘那些花儿
but his father immediately stopped him
但父亲立马制止了
and said, that he could not touch anything or takeanything away from the bower
告诉他，不能碰“凉棚”里的任何东西，更不能拿走
because otherwise it would start raining very heavily.
不然，立马就会天降暴雨
Oh! It's ten to five, Barrie.
噢，Barrie，5点差十分了
Yep.
恩
With the chief's warning fresh in their minds,
酋长的警告还在耳畔回荡
Barrie and the team make an early start and head for the hide.
Barrie和他的小组一早出发去寻找“凉棚”
Well, we've reached the hide just at sunrise, so we're just gonna get set up as quickly as we can.
我们正好赶在日出之前抵达，所以得尽快准备好
With knowledgeable guides, finding the bowers wasn't the problem.
在经验丰富的向导带领下，找到“凉棚”并不难
And who could miss such obvious structures?
谁会错过这么明显的建筑呢？
It was now a waiting game for Barrie,
现在，Barrie只能等待了
heavily concealed in his camouflaged hide.
躲在伪装过的帐篷里
OK, it's 6.30,
好了，6点半了
so I'm just waiting now for the bird to come, hoping that
我只是在等鸟的出现，并希望
he doesn't suspect that anything is here
它不会发现这里有任何异样
and that we can get some natural behaviour.
然后我们能拍下它们自然的行为
I've just heard the bowerbird call just to the right of the hide.
我刚听到帐篷右边有造园鸟的叫声
I can hear the bird outside, it's plucking on the fabric of the hide.
我能听见外面的鸟叫，它在拨弄帐篷表面的帆布
I've just noticed that the bird has pulled a Snickers wrapper out
我注意到它将帐篷底下的一块包装纸
of the bottom of the hide and has added it to its display.
扯了下来，拿回去展览了
It was a very strange decoration
这是个奇怪的装饰
which I had to remove at the end of the day.
我必须在天黑时将它移走
Had Barrie tempted fate by removing the wrapper and ignoring the chief's warning?
是Barrie不顾酋长的警告，冒不必要的险将那个包装纸拿走
Or was this just rainforest living up to its name?
还是，这场雨只是雨林里司空见惯的？（雨林嘛）
When it pours like this, filming becomes virtually impossible.
像这样的磅礴大雨，拍摄已经不可能了
Soon the weather improved and Barrie returned once more to the hide.
不久天气就转好了，Barrie又一次返回帐篷
This time his lunch box was firmly sealed.
这一次，他进行的很顺利
The bird is very keen on these little tiny metallic ladybirds
这只鸟很喜爱这种泛着金属光泽的小瓢虫
and they're a bit put out being put there in this bower,
而它们会从里面的位置爬出来
so, they start crawling off, they're very slowly making their way
它们开始分散，慢慢地爬
over the moss and they just about get to the edge of display
爬过苔藓地毯，刚要爬出展览区域
and then the bowerbird notices and goes and collects them and puts them back again,
然后被造园鸟发现了，又把它们重新弄回去
so they're kind of in this endless cycle of trying to escape from the bower,
所以，它们一次又一次地试图从造园鸟那里逃走
they're just, they can never quite get away.
但它们永远也逃不掉
However for the male bowerbird and Barrie the female was still proving a problem.
对Barrie和雄鸟来说，雌鸟也是个大问题
The female did come down,but she was quite nervous
雌鸟确实下来了，但它很警觉
near the entrance to the bower, so we didn't get very much of that.
在接近凉棚入口处，我们不能靠的太近
This was a real concern,
这真令人担心
because the courtship behaviour was key to our story.
因为我们故事的关键就是它们的求爱行为
He's just done a 10-hour stint,
他完成了10小时的工作
been a really nice day so we're just hoping it's gone well.
天气不错，所以我们希望一切顺利
Another day's filming over, and still little to show for it.
又一天的拍摄结束了，但没什么值得表现的
10 hours in the hide.
在帐篷里呆10小时
Fortunately filming is over for the day,
幸好那天的拍摄结束了
we're just gonna go and collect Barrie again.
我们准备走，又遇到了Barrie
Did you see a mate today?
今天有拍到交配么？
No, no, mating.
没，没有
Everything else is going well but we haven't got the mating.
其它的都进展顺利，就是没拍到交配场面
The fact I was getting such good footage of the male meant he'd obviously got used to the hide.
事实上，我已经取得不错的进展了，雄鸟已经明显习惯了帐篷
But the visiting females were still wary of it.
但是来访的雌鸟还是对它很提防
The females did seem a bit nervous,so I took the decision to push the hide back,
雌鸟看起来很紧张，所以我决定把帐篷后移
just to get more distance from the birds, the other thing I've done is recessed the lens
跟鸟儿们距离远一点，另外我还得调整镜头
and we put this vegetation all around it, so I'm hoping that's gonna provide more female behaviour.
我们把这种植物放在镜头周围，希望雌鸟能更有表现
There were few filming days left,it was crucial Barrie's adjustments paid off.
拍摄只剩下几天了，对Barrie的考验到了紧要关头
The male has just run into the bower and started calling
雄鸟刚跑进凉棚，开始叫唤
so I think that means there might be a female coming.
所以我想，雌鸟可能要来了
It struck me, here we both were waiting in the darkness,
我们在黑暗里等着
the male trying to attract the female,
雄鸟努力着吸引雌鸟
and I was just hoping that I'd got it right this time and it was more than just a fleeting visit.
我只希望没问题，雌鸟这次不会只是短暂的探访
Working in a hide involves hours of prolonged inactivity
在帐篷里静止不动呆了好几小时
punctuated by the most intense moments of action.
被最为紧张的时刻打断了
This was the crucial moment the whole team had worked towards.
这是整个摄制组所期待的决定性时刻
Everything was falling into place for Barrie,
对Barrie来说，求爱行为
the behaviour unfolding.
有条不紊地进行着
Right, that's good,think we're in action.
好，很好，我们开始拍了
21 days in a hide,
在帐篷里呆了21天
astonishing patience and perseverance.
惊人的耐心和毅力
This has never been filmed before.
这些以前从未被拍摄过
Such effort and endeavour for a crucial piece of behaviour that's over in a matter of seconds.
如此努力和付出只为那关键的几秒钟的行为
Would you like to shake my hand, Stephen?
Stephen，愿意和我握个手么？
What does that mean? Well, we got the mating.
什么意思？   额，我们拍到了交配
You got the mating? Yeah, yeah, we got the mating.
你们拍到了？   是的，拍到了
Oh, wow. Yeah, so really good day, brilliant day, yeah but just, just amazing.
哇哦，真是美好的一天，明亮的一天，太神奇了
I must have - well, what is it -three weeks I've spent sitting in this hide, and I just didn't think
我应该在这个帐篷里呆了三星期，我从没想过
we'd ever get it, cos we're running out of days, only a few left now, so, so to get that this week is,
我们能拍到，因为我们没多少时间了……然后，这周就拍到了
is just incredible and it was a really, really good, really good behaviour, so I'm delighted.
太不可思议了，真是太好了，我很高兴
Success! This was Barrie's last filming trip for the Birds episode
成功了！这是Barrie在鸟的这一集的最后一次拍摄
and what a befitting end.
多么好的一个结尾